{"tossups": [{"question": "Pierre Landais [[lahn-DEH]] supported a rebellion against this man by the Duke of Brittany. This husband of Anne Neville faced a revolt by the Duke of Buckingham after this man seized the throne from the child of his brother, Edward IV. In late 2012, this man's skeleton was identified beneath the former site of Greyfriars Church. A landing at Milford Haven in 1485 was a precursor to this man becoming the last English king to die in battle. For ten points, name this man who lost the Battle of Bosworth Field to the future Tudor king, Henry VII.", "answer": "<b><u>Richard III</u></b> (prompt on \"Richard\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This figure revealed the island of Anaphe [[AH-nah-feh]] in order to shelter the Argonauts. Heracles completed his labors for Eurystheus [[yoo-RISS-thee-us]] at this being's command. This deity won a music contest against Pan and turned King Midas's ears into those of a donkey. The patron deity of Delphi, this figure was often conflated with Helios, god of the sun. For ten points, name this Greek god of prophecy, archery, and music, the twin brother of Artemis.", "answer": "<b><u>Apollo</u></b> (or <b><u>Apollon</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "Near the end of this decade, Amalia Post led a successful campaign to enact women's suffrage in the Wyoming Territory, though the lack of nationwide women\u2019s enfranchisement led Elizabeth Cady Stanton to oppose the 15th amendment which was passed during this decade. Activism in this decade followed a four-year conflict that ended with the assassination of Abraham Lincoln following the surrender of Robert E. Lee. For ten points, name this decade during which Reconstruction began after the U.S. Civil War.", "answer": "<b><u>1860</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Graham Stevenson criticized this show for erroneously portraying Winston Churchill as Home Secretary during one period. In this series, December 3, 1919, is decided upon as Black Star Day on which one group challenges Billy Kimber\u2019s pitches at the Worcester [[WOO-ster]] Races. Sam Neill portrays an Ulster Protestant policeman in this show following and titled for an historical street gang comprised of working class men who dressed in distinctive tailored clothes. For ten points, name this BBC crime drama which focuses on historical rivalries in Birmingham.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Peaky Blinders</u></b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this city, Shig Murao [[myuh-RAO]] was arrested for selling an \"obscene\" book written by a local author, but Judge Clayton Horn ruled that <em>Howl</em> was protected by the First Amendment. This city's Beyond Shelter anti-drugs program was created by its mayor, Art Agnos, and Lawrence Ferlinghetti co-founded this city's City Lights bookstore. A large Finnish community used to live in this city's Castro district, and this city was the location of the Summer of Love in its Haight [[HATE]]-Ashbury district. For ten points, name this city in northern California.", "answer": "<b><u>San Francisco</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man established <em>rakuichi</em> [[rah-koo-EE-chee]] open markets and <em>rakuza</em> guilds. Straw dummy troops and a thunderstorm helped this man win the Battle of Okehazama [[oh-keh-hah-ZAH-mah]], where he first noticed the talents of his sandal-bearer, who later succeeded him. Akechi Mitsuhide [[ah-KEH-chee mih-tsoo-HEE-deh]] caught this man in Kyoto and forced his suicide in the Honn\u014d-ji Incident. For ten points, name this Japanese daimyo [[DIE-myoh]] and unifier who preceded the rule of Toyotomi Hideyoshi [[toh-yoh-TOH-mee hih-deh-YOH-shee]].", "answer": "<b><u>Oda</u><u>Nobunaga</u></b> (accept either underlined portion)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Jean McCormick claimed that a group of unsent letters this person wrote proved that she was this person's child. A rescue of Captain Egan may have led to the best known nickname given to this figure, who was said to have chased Jack McCall with a meat cleaver after McCall murdered an acquaintance. This woman was once employed as an assistant to a madam in Deadwood, where she had arrived as part of a wagon train including \"Wild Bill\" Hickok. For ten points, name this storyteller from Buffalo Bill's Wild West Show.", "answer": "<b><u>Calamity Jane</u></b> (accept Martha Jane <b><u>Cannary</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A party that has called for a parliamentary system in this country is the Democratic Patriots' Movement. The death of Chokri Belaid [[beh-lah-EED]] in this country led to accusations that the perpetrators were linked to the Ennahda Movement. In 2015, twenty tourists were killed in a terrorist attack on this country\u2019s Bardo National Museum. Zine [[ZEE-neh]] El Abidine [[ah-bih-DEE-neh]] Ben Ali was ousted as leader of this country following protests that began after a street vendor set himself on fire in 2011. The Arab Spring began in, for ten points, what North African country?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Tunisia</u></b> (accept al-Jumh\u016br\u012byah at-<b><u>T\u016bnis\u012byah</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "It's not fish, but the Mataf\u00e8re [[mah-tah-FEHR]] Tower was constructed to protect workers who collected this good. False bottoms known as <em>faux culls</em> were often worn by women who smuggled this good, a crime punishable by up to ten years on a galley. This good was collected in provincial granaries before it was sold with a tax known as the <em>gabelle</em>. <em>Faux saunage</em> [[foh soh-NAWZH]] involved the fraudulent upselling of, for ten points, what food preservative often found in mines and seawater?", "answer": "<b><u>Salt</u></b> (accept <b><u>Sodium Chloride</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "George Crawford was appointed Secretary of War by this president, but later resigned due to the Galphin Affair. The State of Deseret was founded during the presidency of this man who had defeated Democrat Lewis Cass. Many historians believe that bad water from the Washington sewers caused this man\u2019s death by cholera. For his victories during the Second Seminole War, this man earned the nickname \u201cOld Rough and Ready.\u201d For ten points, name this twelfth U.S. president, who was elected in 1848.", "answer": "Zachary <b><u>Taylor</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A variant of this holiday is celebrated in Latin America as D\u00eda de la Raza. The first parade for this holiday was established by Nicola Larco in San Francisco, and in 2017, the city of Akron drew the ire of its Italian-American community by attempting to replace this holiday with Indigenous Peoples\u2019 Day. Usually held in October, this day is widely celebrated on the island of Hispaniola. For ten points, name this holiday which commemorates a man who was long thought to have discovered the New World in 1492.", "answer": "<b><u>Columbus Day</u></b> (accept <b><u>Day of the Race</u></b>; accept <b><u>Dia de la Raza</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "These events were intentionally ignored by General Anton Denikin during the White Terror, as he believed the victims to be communists. An early example of these events occurred when residents of Strasbourg believed that certain residents engaged in \"host desecration\" and \"blood libel.\" In the nineteenth century, the Pale of Settlement became a hotbed for these violent reprisals, which were motivated by antisemitism. For ten points, name these massacres of Jewish populations in Eastern Europe.", "answer": "<b><u>Pogrom</u></b>s (prompt on descriptive answers such as \"attacks on Jews\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man's collaboration with Hilda Solis led to a $10 million fund to provide illegal immigrants with legal assistance. In Echo Park, this man helped create Historic Filipinotown. Antonio Villaraigosa [[vee-yah-rai-GOH-sah]] preceded this man as mayor of a certain city, the first Jewish holder of that position. In 2020, this man claimed \u201cthis is not 1992\u201d as part of a promise to not deploy the National Guard as had been done during his city\u2019s Rodney King Riots. For ten points, name this Los Angeles mayor, elected in 2013.", "answer": "Eric Michael <b><u>Garcetti</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "The last ruler with this title, Mahmud IV, met his downfall at the hands of the kingdom of Djenn\u00e9 [[jeh-NEH]], which was supported by Moroccan fusiliers. The first man to hold this royal title led a confederation of Mandinka people in their attempt to subjugate the Sosso king Sumanguru, leading to a victory at Kirina. A man with this title devalued the worth of gold in Egypt due to his generosity while on <em>hajj</em>. For ten points, gave this term for a Malian ruler, held by men such as Musa I.", "answer": "<b><u>Mansa</u></b> (accept <b><u>Mansa</u></b> Musa; prompt on \u201cRuler,\u201d \u201cEmperor,\u201d \u201cSultan,\u201d or \u201cKing\u201d of \u201cMali\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "One of these texts describes an apocalyptic \u201cWar of Divisions.\" The Community Rule is one of these texts, the finding of which led to a reassessment of accusations that a work presented by Moses Shapira was a forgery. A group of Bedouins discovered these works in a series of twelve caves in Qumran [[KOOM-ron]]. Debates exist as to whether the Zadokites or the Essenes are responsible for these texts, most of which are housed in the Shrine of the Book in Jerusalem. For ten points, name these Jewish manuscripts found in the West Bank along a namesake body of water.", "answer": "<b><u>Dead Sea Scroll</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Qumran Cave</u></b> Scrolls before mentioned)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "An employee of this company named John Rabe helped rescue victims during the Nanking Massacre. This company's founder created a dynamo that did not require permanent magnets, independently of Charles Wheatstone, and invented a form of telegraphy that relied on needles rather than Morse Code. An alternator built by this company powered the first instance of street lighting, which occurred in the United Kingdom. One of this company's factories in Bobreck was among those worked by prisoners at Auschwitz. Based in Bavaria, for ten points, what is this German industrial conglomerate?", "answer": "<b><u>Siemens</u></b> AG (accept <b><u>Siemens</u></b> and Halske AG; accept <b><u>Siemens</u></b>-Halske; accept <b><u>Siemens</u></b>-Schuckert)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This city contains tree-like structures that house plant beds in Supertree Grove, part of the Gardens by the Bay enhancement program announced by Prime Minister Lee Hsien [[she-EN]] Loong in 2005. This city gave its name to the British naval defense plan for their eastern empire after World War One. Stamford Raffles established a trading post at what became this city on the eastern end of the Strait of Malacca. Off the southern tip of the Malay Peninsula, for ten points, what is this city-state in southeast Asia which has been self-governed since 1959?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Singapore</u></b> (or Republik <b><u>Singapura</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In what is now this state, Peter Parker and Henry Clinton\u2019s forces were rebuffed from taking a city due to William Moultrie\u2019s defense of a namesake fort on Sullivan\u2019s Island. Over five thousand Continental troops under Benjamin Lincoln were captured at a siege in this state, in which the guerilla tactics of native son Francis Marion earned him the nickname \"the Swamp Fox.\u201d The Battles of Waxhaws and Camden were fought in, for ten points, what state which also faced the Siege of Charleston?", "answer": "<b><u>South Carolina</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This man wrote the memoir</u> </b><em><b><u>Advance and Retreat</u></b></em><b><u> partly in response to claims</u></b> <b><u>made by Joseph Johnston. Wounds that this man sustained at Chickamauga led to the</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> amputation of his right leg. A failed \u201cPickett\u2019s Charge of the West\u201d was conducted by this man\u2019s troops at his disastrous defeat at Franklin. That defeat occurred a month before this man was defeated in a December 1864 battle against his former instructor (*) </b>George Thomas at Nashville. For ten points, name this Confederate general known for his reckless aggressiveness.", "answer": "John Bell <b><u>Hood</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In Muslim mythology, this man was a Palestinian disciple of Christ who was</u></b> <b><u>killed three times by the king of Mosul, only to resurrect himself each time. According</u></b> <b><u>to tradition, this saint served as a member of (+)</u> Diocletian\u2019s Praetorian Guard until he was sentenced to death after not renouncing his Christian faith. Crusader states like the Genoese Republic used this saint\u2019s (*) </b>namesake cross as their ensign. For ten points, name this Catholic saint who legendarily slayed a dragon in Libya.", "answer": "Saint <b><u>George</u></b> of Lydda", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man\u2019s first spaceflight was as a pilot on Gemini 10. This man was the first</u></b> <b><u>person to conduct multiple space walks and designed a mission patch based on an</u></b> <b><u>illustration from</u> </b><em><b><u>Water, Prey, and Game Birds of North America</u></b></em><b><u>. A book of 18 (+)</u></b> <b>rendezvous scenarios was created by this man, who was the subject of the quote \"not since Adam has any human known such (*) </b>solitude.\" Alone in the <em>Columbia</em> while the <em>Eagle</em> descended, for ten points, what man was the crewmate of Buzz Aldrin and Neil Armstrong during Apollo 11?", "answer": "Michael <b><u>Collins</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>During this government, a merger between the Parti Communiste and the</u></b> <b><u>Radical Socialists was overseen by Jewish prime minister Leon Blum. With Great</u></b> <b><u>Britain, this government agreed to pursue the policy of appeasement and award</u></b> <b><u>Germany the (+)</u> Sudetenland under \u00c9douard Daladier [[dah-lah-DYEH]]. This government was first established during the chaos of the (*) </b>Franco-Prussian War and the fall of Emperor Napoleon III\u2019s regime. For ten points, name this government which collapsed after Nazi Germany\u2019s 1940 invasion of France and was succeeded by the Vichy government.", "answer": "French <b><u>Third Republic</u></b> (prompt on \u201cFrance\u201d before mentioned; accept La <b><u>Troisi\u00e8me R\u00e9publique</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The</u> </b><em><b><u>Six Steeds of Zhao Mausoleum</u></b></em><b><u> was made in this dynasty, and a form of</u></b> <b><u>lead-glazed \"egg-and-spinach\" pottery known as</u> </b><em><b><u>sancai</u></b></em><b><u> is particularly associated</u></b> <b><u>with this dynasty. One of this dynasty's kilns was located at Tongguan, and this</u></b> <b><u>dynasty's Giant Wild Goose Pagoda survived the (+)</u> 1556 Shaanxi [[SHAHN-SHE]] Earthquake. A poet from this dynasty wrote \"Waking from Drunkenness on a Spring Day\" and a work which begins \"Before my bed there's a pool of light,\" the poem (*) </b>\"Quiet Night Thought.\" For ten points, Li Bai wrote during what Chinese dynasty?", "answer": "<b><u>Tang</u></b> [[TAHNG]] Dynasty (accept <b><u>Tang</u></b> Empire)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One portion of this trail that passed along the Purgatoire [[PER-guh-twah]]</u></b> <b><u>River was referred to as the Mountain Route. A pioneer of this trail named William</u></b> <b><u>Becknell left from the Boonslick region near one of its termini at Franklin. (+)</u></b> <b>Comanche traders collected tolls along this route, which contained Fort Dodge. This trail was rendered largely obsolete in 1880 with the advent of the (*) </b>railroad in its central region. Passing through Colorado and Kansas en route to the Missouri River, for ten points, what trail had an end in a namesake New Mexico city?", "answer": "<b><u>Santa Fe</u></b> Trail", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Hotel of York was the site of negotiations for this treaty, of which the</u></b> <b><u>resolution of debts and the opening of the Mississippi River were key negotiating</u></b> <b><u>points. Concessions in present-day (+)</u> states including Ohio helped double the size of one party\u2019s territory in this treaty with the cession of the Northwest Territory. The Comte de Rochambeau [[roh-shahm-BOH]] helped bring about this treaty by assisting one side in defeating the forces of (*) </b>Charles Cornwallis at Yorktown. For ten points, name this treaty which ended the American Revolution.", "answer": "Treaty of <b><u>Paris</u></b> of <b><u>1783</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's government required the blind and deaf to be educated in the</u></b> <b><u>Elementary Education Act. After Secretary Cavendish was assassinated, this man</u></b> <b><u>ordered arbitrary detainment via the Irish Coercion Act. This man attacked the (+)</u></b> <b>Bulgarian Horrors of the Ottomans in the Midlothian Campaign, bombarded Alexandria, and, in his second ministry, fought the Mahdi in Sudan. Extending voting to (*) </b>laborers in the 1884 Reform Act, for ten points, who was this \"Murderer of Gordon,\" a Liberal British prime minister and rival of Benjamin Disraeli?", "answer": "William Ewart <b><u>Gladstone</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>These people led the 1990 Baren Township riot, and members of this ethnic</u></b> <b><u>group who formed the Grey Wolves may have been responsible for the 2015 Bangkok</u></b> <b><u>bombing. 31 people were killed in a 2014 attack on a railway station by separatists of</u></b> <b><u>this ethnic group. These people were (+)</u> sent to \"Vocational Education and Training Centers,\" in which they faced abuse during the \"people's (*) </b>war on terror.\" Many of these people live in historical Dzungaria in Urumqi [[oo-ROOM-chee]], the capital of Xinjiang [[SHIN-JAHNG]]. For ten points, name these persecuted Turks in China.", "answer": "<b><u>Uighur</u></b>s [[WEE-goors]]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}], "bonuses": []}